Guide to the Daniel Washington Norton Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Daniel Washington Norton papers
1813-1878
1830-1878
MS 376
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
15.5
The papers contain correspondence and other records of Loomis and Norton, a paper manufacturing firm in Windsor Locks, Connecticut. The papers also contain records of several textile and mining companies and those of Connecticut Canal Railroad and other companies. A small amount of personal correspondence and account books are also found in the papers.
Norton, Daniel Washington, 1799-1874
Arrangement
Financial papers arranged alphabetically by organization.
Biographical / Historical
Daniel Washington Norton was born in Suffield, Connecticut in 1799, the son of Daniel and Lucy (King) Norton. He was educated in Suffield schools and Amherst College where he studied surveying.
Norton was one of the most outstanding men of Suffield. He was always in the front ranks of business affairs and progress. He was also actively involved in the civic matters of Suffield.
Daniel Norton was one of the first to see the possibilities of the insurance business. He became an agent of the Aetna Fire and Life Insurance Company in their early years. He was very successful and often made trips as far as Ohio. He was also financially interested in several industrial concerns, among them were the Windsor Knitting Factory, the Lacowsic Woolen Company and the Eagle Paper Mill. With John W. Loomis, he formed the partnership of Loomis and Norton. They were engaged extensively in cigar manufacturing. Norton was one of the founders of the First National Bank of Suffield and served as its first president.
In 1858 when the memory of the Reverend Benjamin Ruggles was honored, Norton was the primary planner of the celebration. Twelve years later, in 1870, at the Bicentennial of Suffield, he was the head of the committee and much of the success of that memorable occasion was due to his untiring efforts. He was life-long member of the Congregational Church of Suffield, and with his family, active in its welfare.
Daniel Washington Norton married Mindwell Pease, daughter of Joseph Pease. They had four children: John Hughes Norton, Ellen (Mrs. George Loomis), Lucy (who died in childhood), Elizabeth (Mrs. Calvin W. Philleo), and Emily. After the death of his first wife, Norton married Augusta Knowles, who survived him.
(Biographical information courtesy of Frances Edwards, Rare Book Dealer)
In addition to this inventory there is a separate card drawer. See the Reference Archivist for its location.
Scope and Contents
The papers contain correspondence and other records of Loomis and Norton, a paper manufacturing firm in Windsor Locks, Connecticut. The papers also contain records of several textile and mining companies and those of Connecticut Canal Railroad and other companies. A small amount of personal correspondence and account books are also found in the papers.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Business; Canals -- Massachusetts; Mines and mineral resources; Mineral industries -- Finance -- Connecticut; Papermaking -- Connecticut; Railroads; Textile industry -- Connecticut; Connecticut -- Economic conditions; Connecticut -- Industries; Connecticut; Suffield (Conn.); Windsor Locks (Conn.) -- Economic conditions; Account books; Manufacturers; Mineral industries -- Connecticut; Allen, E. T. (Edward Tyson), 1875-1942; Hills, Lewis M.; Loomis, Bryon; Norton, Daniel Washington, 1799-1874; Norton, John Hughes; Stowe, Joseph D.; Agawan Canal Company; Boston Copper and Sulfuric Acid Company; Bridgeport Copper and Sulfuric Acid Company; Clinton Line Railroad Company; Franklin Paper Company; Hartford Mining and Smelting Company; King and Norton Lumber Company; Lacowsic Woolen Company; Loomis and Norton; Magic Paper Collar Company; Sequassen Woolen Company; Silver Series Mining Company; Suffield Gold, Silver, and Copper Mining Company; Windsor Knitting and Manufacturing Company; Windsor Knitting and Woolen Company
- Inventory, 1813, 1830-1878
  - Loomis & Norton
    - 1866-1869 (Box 1)
    - 1870 (Box 2)
    - 1871 January-June (Box 3)
    - 1871 July-December (Box 4)
    - 1872 January-May (Box 5)
    - 1872 June-September (Box 6)
    - 1872 October-December (Box 7)
    - 1873 January-March (Box 8)
    - 1873 April-June (Box 9)
    - 1873 July-September (Box 10)
    - 1873 October-December (Box 11)
    - 1874 January-March (Box 12)
    - 1874 April-June (Box 13)
    - 1874 July-September (Box 14)
    - 1874 October-December (Box 15)
    - 1875 January-March (Box 16)
    - 1875 April-June (Box 17)
    - 1875 July-September (Box 18)
    - 1875 October-December (Box 19)
    - 1876 January-April (Box 20)
    - 1876 May-August (Box 21)
    - 1876 September-December (Box 22)
    - 1877 January-March (Box 23)
    - 1877 April-June (Box 24)
    - 1877 July-December (Box 25)
    - 1878 January-April (Box 26)
    - 1878 May-December (Box 27)
    - Cash journal, 1868-1875 (Box 28)
    - Order books, 1869-1871, 1872-1875 (Box 28)
    - General journals, 1868-1873, 1873-1877 (Box 28)
  - Textile industries
    - Lacowsic Woolen Company
      - 1866 - 1868 (Box 29)
      - 1869 (Box 30)
      - 1870 - 1871 (Box 31)
      - ADD I, 1866 - 1873 (Box 32)
    - Windsor Knitting and Manufacturing Company
      - 1852 August - 1853 October (Box 33)
      - 1853 October - 1857 December (Box 34)
    - Agawan Canal Company
      - Correspondence, 1849 - 1873 (Box 35)
      - 1847 - 1873 (Box 36)
    - Sequassen Woolen Company, 1857-1863 (Box 37)
    - Hills, Lewis M. and Allen, Edward T., 1857-1863 (Box 38)
  - Insurance, 1838-1873, undated (Box 39)
  - Magic Paper Collar Company, 1871-1873 (Box 39)
  - Suffield, Conn.: First National Bank, 1863-1871 (Box 39)
  - Suffield, Conn.: Town Affairs, 1860-1873 (Box 39)
  - Yale University: Alumni, 1862-1863 (Box 39)
  - Miscellaneous business letters and papers
    - 1847-1870 (Box 40)
    - 1827-1868, 1871-1874 (Box 41)
  - Personal correspondence, 1859-1873 (Box 42)
  - King and Norton Lumber Company, 1835-1869 (Box 43)
  - Suffield Block, 1850-1860 (Box 44)
  - Mining
    - Suffield Gold, Silver, and Copper Mining Company
      - Correspondence, 1866-1873 (Box 45)
      - Business papers, 1866-1873 (Box 46)
    - Boston Copper and Sulphuric Acid Company, 1870-1873 (Box 47)
    - Bridgeport Copper and Sulphuric Acid Company, 1870-1873 (Box 47)
    - Hartford Mining and Smelting Company, 1865-1869 (Box 47)
    - Metal Works and Stevens Glux Company, 1868-1871 (Box 47)
    - Silver Series Mining Company, 1865-1869 (Box 47)
    - Boston Copper and Sulphuric Acid Company, 1869-1871 (Box 48)
    - Bridgeport Copper and Sulphuric Acid Company, 1869-1871 (Box 48)
    - Hartford Mining and Smelting Company, 1868-1871 (Box 48)
    - Metal Works and Stevens Company, 1867-1873 (Box 48)
    - Silver Series Mining Company, 1865-1871 (Box 48)
    - Suffield Gold, Silver and Copper Mining Company, 1867-1873 (Box 48)
  - Insurance, 1847-1871 (Box 49)
  - King and Norton Lumber Company, 1837-1858 (Box 49)
  - Hathaway (Asahel, 1739-1828) Estate, 1842-1853 (Box 49)
  - Granger (Catherine) Estate, 1846-1849 (Box 49)
  - Hanchett (Samuel) Estate, 1855-1858 (Box 49)
  - Agawan Canal Company, Agawan Paper Company, 1847-1874 (Box 49)
  - Hills, Lewis M. and Allen, Edward T., 1867-1871 (Box 49)
  - Sequassen Woolen Company, 1858-1865 (Box 49)
  - Windsor Knitting and Manufacturing Company, 1850-1858 (Box 49)
  - Norton, Daniel Washington (1799-1874): arithmetic book, commonplace book, letter book, and personal correspondence (Box 50)
  - King and Norton Lumber Company, 1832-1834 (Box 51)
  - Account books re
    - Family expenses, 1870-1877 (Box 52)
    - Estate of Asahel Hathaway and miscellaneous financial accounts, 1830-1869, 1830-1853 (Box 52)
    - Miscellaneous accounts and records of daily business transactions, 1837-1849 (Box 52)
    - Accounts with Newton and Pomroy, 1868-1870 (Box 53)
    - Accounts with Horace Sheldon
      - 1853-1859, 1862-1864 (Box 53)
    - Accounts with Farmers & Mechanics Bank, 1843-1851 (Box 53)
  - Arithmetical tables, 1813 (Box 53)
  - Clinton Line Railroad, 1854-1873 (Box 54)
  - Textile industries
    - Windsor Knitting and Manufacturing Company
      - Ledger, 1853 April-1854 March (Box 55)
      - Journal, 1853 April-1854 March (Box 55)
  - Mining
    - Silver Series Mining Company
      - Copies from company ledgers, 1-4, of data on organization and subsequent meetings, 1865-1866 (Box 55)
  - Oversize materials
    - Legal, financial, and insurance documents
      - Agawam Canal Company [cotton mill], 1849-1855 (Box 56)
      - Clinton Railroad, 1850s (Box 56)
      - Suffield Gold, Silver, and Copper Mining Company, 1866-1868 (Box 56)
      - Windsor Knitting and Manufacturing Company, 1853 (Box 56)
      - Property purchases, Circa 1866 (Box 56)